Guide to the Roy M. Huffington Naval Papers, 1942-2005 MS 611
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Roy M. Huffington Naval Papers, 1942-2005
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Huffington, Roy M.
MS 611
3.75 Linear Feet (6 boxes + oversize material)
This collection is part of a wider compilation of Roy M. Huffington's personal and professional papers. These materials encompass his service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. The materials reflect his continued interest in both the Navy and the history of the conflict. This collection consists of service records, personal correspondence, WWII aerial intelligence photographs, records from various veterans' organizations, and personal research.
Biographical Note
Roy M. Huffington was born in Tomball, Texas on Oct 4, 1917. The son of an oil man, he earned his bachelors in geology from Southern Methodist University in 1938, and earned a Ph.D. in geology from Harvard in 1942. After serving aboard the USS Hornet as a lieutenant during World War II, he left the Navy and went to work for Humble Oil. In 1956, Huffington left Humble to start his own business with the money he had saved over the previous decade, Roy M. Huffington, Inc. or as it was also known, "Huffco". The company made a number of successful ventures around the world, most notably the discovery of vast reserves of natural gas in Indonesia in 1972. In 1989, Huffington sold his oil company, and in 1990 President Bush appointed him to Ambassador to Austria. Among his many other commitments he also served as chairman of the Asia Society and the Salzburg Seminar. Huffington passed away in 2008 at the age of 90.
Scope and Content
This collection is a subset of a wider gathering of Roy M. Huffington's personal and professional papers. The bulk of the materials are aerial intelligence photographs from Huffington's service as a Photographic Interpretation Officer. Subjects include ships, aircraft, geography, and combat. A significant portion of the records pertain superficially to Huffington's service aboard the USS Hornet from early 1944 until the end of the war under Admiral "Jocko" Clark. These materials include photos and ephemera related to the Hornet along with its crew, deck logs, correspondence. Additionally there are books and manuscripts collected by Huffington.
Other records include Huffington's personal correspondence with family and loved ones during his naval service, his official Navy records and correspondence, materials related to various veteran organizations and clubs, including the US Navy League, the US Navy Memorial Foundation, US Navy Photographic Intelligence veterans, and the USS Hornet Club. There is also a small assortment of book manuscripts, articles, and other material reflecting Huffington's continued interest in the US Navy during WWII.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Use Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Related Materials
Please refer to Roy M. Huffington Personal and Professional papers,1972-2009, MS 688; Roy M. Huffington Oil company records, 1977-2006 MS 575 for more information on the company and Mr. Huffington; Roy M. Huffington Ambassadorial Papers, 1988-2008 MS 617; as well as the Huffington and allied families' papers, 1650-1955 MS 883.
Index Terms
Subjects
World War (1939-1945); Naval History -- United States; Military
- Series I: Aerial Intelligence Photographs, 1943-1945; 179250
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 4/1944-6/1944; 179256 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 7/1-19/1944; 179257 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 7/20-28/1944; 179258 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 8/1944-9/1944; 179259 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 12/1994-2/1945; 179260 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 1945; 179261 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 1945; 179262 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Assorted Photos, n.d.; 179263 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, Memos, Intelligence Reports, 179264 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 7/1-19/1944; 179265 (Box 4)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 7/20/-28/1944; 179266 (Box 4)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 8/1944-9/1944; 179267 (Box 4)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 12/1944-2/1945; 179268 (Box 4)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 1945; 179269 (Box 4)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Aerial Photos, 1945; 179270 (Box 4)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Assorted Photos, n.d.; 179271 (Box 4)
  - USS Belleau Wood (CVL 24) ) Aerial Photos, 4/6/1944-4/21/1944; 179272 (Box 1)
  - USS Bataan (CVL-29) Aerial Photos, 4/21/1944; 179273 (Box 1)
  - USS Yorktown (CV-10) Aerial Photos, 179274 (Box 1)
  - USS Bennington (CV-20) Aerial Photos, 179275 (Box 1)
  - USS Langley (CVL-27) Aerial Photos, 6/13/1944; 179276 (Box 1)
  - USS San Jacinto (CVL-30) Aerial Photos, 3/24/1944-4/2/1945; 179277 (Box 1)
  - USS Monterey (CVL-26), 6/19/1944-6/20/1944; 179278 (Box 1)
  - USS Intrepid (CV-11) Aerial Photos, 4/16/1945; 179279 (Box 1)
  - USS Essex (CV-9) Aerial Photos, 3/23/1945; 179280 (Box 1)
  - USS Wasp (CV-18) Aerial Photos, 2/18/1945-?; 179281 (Box 1)
  - USS Cowpens (CVL-25) Aerial Photos, 4/21/1944-4/30/1944; 179282 (Box 1)
  - Unknown Ship (CV-17?) Aerial Photos, 1945; 179283 (Box 1)
  - USS Belleau Wood (CVL-24) Aerial Photos, 4/21/1944-3/31/1944; 179284 (Box 5)
  - USS Bataan (CVL-29) Aerial Photos, 6/20/1944-7/11/1944; 179285 (Box 5)
  - USS Yorktown (CV-10) Aerial Photos, 1944-1945; 179286 (Box 5)
  - USS Yorktown (CV-10) Aerial Photos, 1944; 179287 (Box 5)
  - USS Bennington (CV-20) Aerial Photos, 1945; 179288 (Box 5)
  - USS San Jacinto (CVL-30) Aerial Photos, 4/7/1945; 179289 (Box 5)
  - USS Intrepid (CV-11) Aerial Photos, March?; 179290 (Box 5)
  - USS Wasp (CV-18) Aerial Photos, 1944-1945; 179291 (Box 5)
  - USS Randolph (CV-15) Aerial Photos, 5/18/1945; 179292 (Box 5)
  - Unknown Ship, 3/12/1944-?; 179293 (Box 5)
  - Aerial Photos, 11/1943; 2,3,6/1944; 179294 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - USS Yorktown Aerial Photos, Vari Guam Conf., 1944-07; 179295 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Aerial Photos, 8,9,12/1944; 179296 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Aerial Photos, 1/1945; 179297 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Aerial Photos, 3-4/1945; 179298 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Aerial Photos, 179299 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series II: USS Hornet, 1944-1945; 179251
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) "Turn 'Off' at Darken Ship" Compilation of Photos by Photo Lab Personnel of the USS Hornet, 179300 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) Correspondence and Ship News Papers, 1944-1945; 179301 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet (CV-12) USS Hornet booklet by Chuck Self, 179302 (Box 1)
  - USS Hornet: Photos, Ephemera, Assorted, 179303 (Box 3)
  - USS Hornet: Coversheet and Deck Log of Officers, 1944-1945; 179304 (Box 3)
  - The United States Ship Hornet (Photocopy), 179305 (Box 3)
  - The Tale of the Hornet compiled by Stanley Blumenthal (2 photocopies), 179306 (Box 3)
  - The Hornet and their Heroic Men by Kenneth M. Glass, 179307 (Box 3)
  - The Saga of the USS Hornet, CV-12 in WWII (Photocopy) by John (Ace) Broughton, 179308 (Box 3)
  - USS Hornet: A Pictorial History by Chuck Shelf, 1997; 179309 (Box 3)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1943-1945; 179252
  - Letter to Sherm from Roy Huffington (photocopy), 4/5/1942; 179310 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (1); Copy on 1 DVD, 1943-1945; 179311 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (2), 1943-1945; 179312 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (1), 1945; 179313 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (2), 1945; 179314 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (3), 1945; 179315 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence on US Navy Stationary (photocopies), 1945; 179316 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Navy Service Records, 1942-1946; 179253
  - United States Naval Training School Year Book, 1942-1943; 179317 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Bluejackets Manual, 1940; 179318 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Naval Officer's Guide by Arthur A. Ageton, 1943; 179348 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - USS Franklin, Bulletin on the USS Franklin, 1945; 179319 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Air Group Seventeen Review, 1944-1945; 179320 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sea Power Vol. 30, No. 2, 1987-01-02 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letter from John Clark McGuire? Re: Midway: The Battle that Doomed Japan, 1989-11-13 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - US Navy: Assorted Records and Correspondence, 1942-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Navy: Notes, Correspondence, Assorted Records, 1942-1955; 179321 (Box 3)
  - Roy Huffington Navy Service Photos and Portraits, 179322 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - USS Hornet - "Solemn Mysteries of the Ancient Order of the Deep" certificate, 1944-05-03 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series V: Veteran Organizations, 1980s-2004; 179254
  - U.S. Navy Photographic Intelligence: Newsletters, Correspondence, Reunion Materials, 179324 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy Photographic Intelligence: Trip to Washington D.C., 9/2-7/1996; 179325 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy Photographic Intelligence: Reunion at Delray Beach, Florida, 1994; 179326 (Box 3)
  - USS Hornet Club Inc.; Copy of correspondence with Joseph Linick on 1 Floppy Disk, 179327 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy: USS San Jacinto, 179328 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy: USS Lexington, 179329 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy: USS Texas, 179330 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy: USS America, New York, 5/23-24/1995; 179331 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy League of the United States, 179332 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy League of Houston, 179333 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy Memorial Foundation, 179334 (Box 3)
- Series VI: Personal Research, 179255
  - Sea Power Vol. 30 No. 2, 1/2/1987; 179335 (Box 3)
  - Letter from John Clark McGuire Re: Midway: The Battle that Doomed Japan, 179336 (Box 3)
  - Articles (Photocopies): "Admiral 'Jock' Clark and Bob Hope;" "Biography of Rear Admiral Joseph James 'Jocko' Clark", 179337 (Box 3)
  - "Harts Command Hailed," New York Times, 2/9/1942; 179338 (Box 3)
  - "Symposium: Air Ops in the Pacific" The Nimitz News, 179339 (Box 3)
  - "Lessons from a World at War" The National Museum of the Pacific War Campaign Exhibit Guide, 179340 (Box 3)
  - The Medallion: WWII Special Edition, 9-10/2005; 179341 (Box 3)
  - Houston PBS TV Schedule, 5/2005: This Month on American Experience; This Month on An Untold Triumph, 179342 (Box 3)
  - List of George Bush Presidential Library Trustees, 179343 (Box 3)
  - Taylor Daily Press: Copy of Archives Search for "Shuffield", 179344 (Box 3)
  - Printout of Amazon.com search for books: Halseys Typhoon, Sea Cobra, Down to the Sea, 179345 (Box 3)
  - Carrier War by Lt. Oliver Jensen, USNR, 179346 (Box 3)
  - Japan 1945 by Joe Bill (Copy), 179347 (Box 3)